<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2026-01-06T18:37:10+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dearest Mahi</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/lett1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dearest Mahi" /><published>2025-12-29T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-29T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/lett1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/lett1/"><![CDATA[<p>Dearest Mahi, You are most welcome in our life. Your arrival has filled every corner of our existence with a meaning we never knew was missing.</p>

<div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center">
    <div class="col-sm-4">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/IMG_2572.JPEG" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<p>It was November of 2024 that we got to witness for the very first time the signal of your life. The test showed those two unmistakable lines, and in that moment, everything changed. You were just so tiny – invisible from outside (funny, isn’t it?) and of course, feelable, not by me, but your momma. She was the first to know you were there, growing, becoming. You definitely were supportive – mostly – and only a few tantrums of your presence through those early weeks of nausea and exhaustion. Ah, maybe that is because you are more like me (taking credit here!) – considerate and gentle, at least most of the time.</p>

<p>Was she ready? I don’t know. Perhaps no one ever truly is. But I am sure she wanted to be ready; 100 percent. She read everything she could, asked every question, prepared her body and mind for you. Was I ready? I think I was not 100 percent – Not that I didn’t want to be, just that I didn’t know how to “start” becoming a poppa. I had never truly held a newborn before, never changed a diaper, never understood what it meant to be responsible for a tiny life. I never did a crash course and not that there exists one – no manual can teach you how to love someone you haven’t met yet. But together, we both were trying to tell each other that “We are Ready.” We held hands through the uncertainty, whispered reassurances in quiet moments, and promised to figure it out together, one day at a time.</p>

<p>I wasn’t there with your momma when she heard the news of you being present inside her. I was thousands of kilometers away, working, living a life that suddenly felt incomplete. I can’t even imagine how she must have felt that day – that singular moment when the sister (nurse) showed her those two lines of life, when possibility became reality. But, I am sure something big must have changed inside her (literally and metaphorically) and will probably remain like that until her last day. A part of her became yours forever. I got your news only over phone while I was going to get my coffee from the little kitchenette 7000 kilometers away from Goa. Her voice was shaking, excited, nervous, all at once. Did I cry in the kitchen? Of course, I did… A lot. The tears came before I could even process what she had said. Did I want to hold your momma and cry out like a baby? Of course, I did. Every cell in my body wanted to be there with her, to share that moment properly, not through a phone screen. Did I feel helpless? A little. The distance felt cruel, unnecessary, wrong. But, Mahi, that day was probably the best day of my life until then. Nothing before or after has matched the pure joy and terror of knowing you were coming.</p>

<p>You had your time inside momma for about 9 months and wow!!! you made our lives beautiful, with your tiny kicks, boxing and probably several rounds of somersaults. We would sit together in the evenings, feeling you move, guessing which part of you was pushing against her belly. We knew you are strong. Your movements were vigorous, determined, like you were already exploring the boundaries of your world.
Then comes the day of the 5th July 2025 – You sent a signal of your coming (you wanted to see the world). Your momma woke up early that morning and knew something was different. You made momma’s life a bit pinkish that day – early morning and later. The contractions started gently, then grew more insistent as the hours passed. I was excited, scared, hungry, worried, and all kinds of emotions and in all its spectrum. Time moved strangely that day, too fast and too slow at once. My heart was beating a few miles a minute. I was sweating and feeling chills at the same time. And I was praying hard to our baba (Shiva) to keep your momma and you very safe. And this one strong emotion cutting through all the chaos – I want you and momma to be safe. That was the only thing that mattered, the only prayer I had. I was ready to face everything afterwards. I had never felt that ready for anything in my life.</p>

<p>We were half-prepared for your arrival (no one is 100% prepared, are they?). We had packed the hospital bag weeks earlier, but somehow it still felt like we had forgotten something essential. We had lunch – though neither of us could eat much (well, I ate. haha!), the anticipation stealing our appetite – and then went for a checkup with the doctor uncle. He examined your momma, told us it was time, and suddenly everything became very real. We had to wait overnight for observation and at about 3 am on the 6th of July, you starting knocking again…almost felt like you are banging the door.</p>

<p>“Push…try hard…” – Doctor uncle said to momma, and she did. She was stronger than I ever knew, braver than I could have been. And, you were there on the 6th of July 2025 at 2.25 PM, weighing 3.02 Kg and visibly so tall (as they said). I saw your tiny face for the first time, scrunched up and perfect.
I saw you and held you in my arms for the very first time at about 5 PM, after they had cleaned you up and checked that you were healthy. It changed everything, in an instance. You were wrapped in a beautiful soft cotton sheet like a subway wrap, only your beautiful, determined face visible. I wanted to feel your tiny fingers wrapped around mine, your eyes trying to focus on my face. But I had to wait for those moments for a few hours. I felt your weight so light but so significant in my arms. You meant everything to me (and us) – Our only true purpose in life. Every decision from that moment forward would be measured against one question: what is best for Mahi? I could go on and on – about that first night, about learning your different cries, about the way you smell, about watching momma feed you – but, when you read this you will probably be old enough to hear them out from me (us) directly. We will sit together, and I will tell you every detail you want to know.</p>

<p>Dearest Mahi, you are most welcome. And, momma and poppa love you loads…</p>

<p>G and T</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You are here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I am waiting.</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/lett0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I am waiting." /><published>2025-02-16T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-16T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/lett0</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/lett0/"><![CDATA[<p>Hey, you!!!</p>

<p>What’s up with you, mate, busy growing?<br />
I am waiting…<br />
To see how you will make life so wholesome and complete again,<br />
worth living… the rest of it…</p>

<p>This is something so blissful I can’t even imagine.<br />
I can almost imagine you holding me, hugging me, running to me, and<br />
I can’t wait to tell you how much I love you…</p>

<p>I am manifesting not a father but a friend in me,<br />
that you can always count on, no matter what, all throughout life<br />
until the last breath that I take.</p>

<p>I know, almost, what kind of father I don’t want to be.<br />
Rest everything we can both work out along the way, eh!!<br />
It is going to be a fun ride with you by my side.</p>

<p>Oh, one more thing I forgot to tell you,<br />
your mom is a bit on the stricter side,<br />
so you know who to run to for things…<br />
But, she is lovely and too much caring…<br />
do not ever hurt her… that’s my wife.</p>

<p>You are just 5 months away, and I can only dream of you now.<br />
Who will you look more like, me or her?<br />
Will you be some weighted average or more complex than that?</p>

<p>It doesn’t matter so much; I hope you take the best of both of us<br />
and leave everything else…<br />
But one thing for sure, I want you to be as curious as me…</p>

<p>Now is the right time to tell you that I cry with happiness and sadness;<br />
I am human, and so will you be, but never worry; I will be there for you. Always…</p>

<p>The world sometimes can be nasty…<br />
But I promise your mother and I will keep you safe while also<br />
teaching you how to love, respect, and care…</p>

<p>More to tell you, but let me let you grow a bit more…</p>

<p>If you are this far, you know I am not good at writing down my feelings.<br />
But I tried… only for you. Nothing else matters!!!</p>

<p>I love you, and I am waiting…</p>

<p>Yours,<br />
T</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You are a miracle.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One day we all will die!</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/death/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One day we all will die!" /><published>2025-02-09T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-09T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/death</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2025/death/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>“Sssiiip… Nothing beats the first sip of coffee.”</strong><br />
I tell myself, sitting in a moderately cozy coffee shop, looking outside the window while people go on with their lives. A baby crying in their mother’s arms, couples walking hand in hand, a guitarist playing and losing himself in the music while people listen, absorbing the dark, rainy, chilled day.</p>

<p>A thought suddenly crosses my mind. Not that it has never come before—perhaps a million times. But today, it feels different.</p>

<p><strong>What’s the point?</strong></p>

<p>One day, I will die. So will everyone else.</p>

<p>What’s the <strong>**ing point of all of this? The chase for a name, the chase for grants, the medals, the respect, the positions? Suddenly, it all feels different. I wonder if it’s the gloomy evening or if it’s just me, alone. No, I think it’s neither. I enjoy my <del>loneliness</del> **solitude</strong>. I enjoy thinking, living, and being by myself.</p>

<p>Is this the so-called <strong>existential crisis</strong>, the one that strikes everyone at some point in life? No, I don’t think so. I am enjoying my existence. Then why does this question of <strong>death</strong> suddenly intrude?</p>

<p>Maybe it has something to do with the coffee.</p>

<p>Okay, let’s just blame the coffee and move forward.</p>

<h4 id="the-unavoidable-truth">The Unavoidable Truth</h4>

<p>One day, we and everyone we know will be gone. Only a handful of what we do or say will matter, and even that—for just a brief moment in time.</p>

<p>With the pace at which technology is evolving, especially AI, this duration might be even shorter. <strong>How much shorter?</strong> Maybe the big tech companies know.</p>

<p>I believe this is the ultimate truth of life: everything we do is just a second-hand way to avoid confronting death, until reality strikes us for good.</p>

<p>We are just <strong>microscopic cosmic dust</strong> running around a tiny blue ball called Earth, fighting with other dust, saying:</p>

<p><strong>“Damn! I am thriving.”</strong></p>

<p>We wear a mask, one that signifies our “un”-true identity, and imagine our own importance. Every single day, we reinforce that mask, doing everything to keep the illusion intact.</p>

<p>From chasing a few hundred likes on a social media post to running after job promotions—it’s all the same. We want to stay <strong>relevant</strong>. We invent purposes, one after another, and live for them.</p>

<p><strong>Only to realize that we are nothing.</strong></p>

<h4 id="the-certainty-of-death">The Certainty of Death</h4>

<p>Am I enjoying thinking about my own death? Of course not. <strong>Nobody enjoys thinking about their own death.</strong></p>

<p>But I believe it is absolutely necessary. Perhaps one of the most important psychological exercises one can do.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Death is the only thing that is certain.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Chapter 2, Verse 27 of the <strong>Bhagavad Gita</strong> says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>jātasya hi dhruvo mṛityur dhruvaṁ janma mṛitasya cha</strong><br />
<strong>tasmād aparihārye ’rthe na tvaṁ śhochitum arhasi</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>(jātasya—for one who has been born; hi—for; dhruvaḥ—certain; mṛityuḥ—death; dhruvam—certain; janma—birth; mṛitasya—for the dead; cha—and; tasmāt—therefore; aparihārye arthe—in this inevitable situation; na—not; tvam—you; śhochitum—lament; arhasi—befitting)</em></p>

<p><strong>“Death is certain for one who has been born, and rebirth is inevitable for one who has died. Therefore, you should not lament over the inevitable.”</strong></p>

<h4 id="the-illusion-of-importance">The Illusion of Importance</h4>

<p>Interestingly, knowingly or unknowingly, my decisions in life have always been shaped by the fact that <strong>one day, I will die</strong>.</p>

<p>Yet, most people spend their entire lives chasing things that do not matter. The very fact that we are all destined for death should make us <strong>love each other more</strong>. But strangely, it does not.</p>

<p>Instead:</p>
<ul>
  <li>We nitpick trivialities.</li>
  <li>We hate each other.</li>
  <li>We despise everyone.</li>
  <li><strong><em>What the f</em></strong>?***</li>
</ul>

<p>We should be choosing values well beyond ourselves. Yet, we let life’s trivialities <strong>consume us</strong>.</p>

<p>We <strong>regret everything</strong>.<br />
We are <strong>happy with nothing</strong>.<br />
We <strong>chase happiness</strong>, yet we have never sat alone and reflected on the fact that <strong>true happiness comes only when we care for something beyond ourselves</strong>.</p>

<p>This is the feeling that draws us to temples, inspires us to raise a family, motivates us to save money, and drives us to buy a car.</p>

<p><strong>All of us chase greatness.</strong></p>

<p>We wonder what legacy we will leave behind.</p>

<p>But in doing so, we often forget: <strong>we are already winners.</strong></p>

<p>We were born winners.<br />
One in millions of sperm fertilized that egg with a probability of <strong><em>1/infinity</em></strong>.</p>

<p>The degrees we chase, the medals we earn, the class, the cars, the house—<strong>they do not define greatness</strong>.</p>

<p>We are already great.<br />
Because we know what to care for and what not to, amid the <strong>utter confusion of life and the certainty of death</strong>.</p>

<h4 id="what-truly-matters">What Truly Matters</h4>

<p>We <strong>do not</strong> have to achieve everything to have a meaningful life.</p>

<p>Instead:</p>
<ul>
  <li>We should <strong>care for others</strong>.</li>
  <li>We should <strong>care for peace</strong>.</li>
  <li>We should <strong>care for the planet</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p>We should slowly loosen the <strong>mask of importance</strong> and soften the <strong>shield of ego</strong>. We should try to impact lives, however small that impact may be.</p>

<p>One day, we too will be <strong>dead and forgotten</strong>, like the tree that was cut down to build the house we live in.</p>

<p>So, let’s just <strong>pause</strong> for a moment.<br />
Let’s <strong>think inward</strong>.<br />
Let’s be <strong>thankful for our existence</strong>.</p>

<p>And let’s just enjoy our own cup of <strong>coffee</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections Over a Cup of Coffee]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shh…Be quiet!</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/silence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shh…Be quiet!" /><published>2024-12-15T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-15T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/silence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/silence/"><![CDATA[<p>After finishing his 12th standard (also called Junior College) in science, he (let’s call “the boy”) got into an engineering college about 350 kilometres away from home, too far away from his grandparents, parents, and sisters. But this distance, although it sounded too much in those early years, will turn out to be some of the defining years of his life that will shape him as a suitable survivor for the upcoming future. Life was going to teach him a few things along the way, but the journey would be memorable nevertheless. This is an experience (and a nightmare!) of his life that he experienced during his travels via the dangerous ghat roads at past midnight. He clearly remembers this night like yesterday and hopes to forget it one day. I wish he just could!</p>

<p>The year was 2010, December, the chilly winter, right after the semester exam. He always anticipated a good journey and looked forward to returning home. His exams were excellent. In fact, he was expecting to score the top rank in the institute. This time, he was joyful about visiting his family, sharing a few days with them, playing with his sisters, and cycling; he loved cycling even then. He booked a ticket to his hometown (Balangir) on a bus that leaves his most beloved city (Berhampur) in the evening around 7 pm.</p>

<p>These evening buses start from Berhampur usually a bit later than the ticket shows (which is nice!), stop at a few local yet big stops, and stop near Bhanjanagar (right before the Kalinga ghat roads start) for a quick dinner. This stop used to be one of his favourites. This is the last time he is roughly conscious before sleeping off and dealing with his motion sickness on the Ghat journey. This time, he got a seat at the far back of the bus (Seat 32), at the tail-end of the 2/2-pushback bus. This journey, he thought, was dreadful, given his issues with motion sickness.</p>

<p>He gets into the bus, sits on the bus, and looks forward to returning home after the stressful university exams. The bus leaves the station with a bus full of passengers. After an hour, the bus conductor (ticket investigator), a tall old man in his late 40s, comes to the back and starts checking tickets. The boy politely asks: “Sir, can you move me to one of the front seats. I feel vomitish at the back. I am going to your last stop (Balangir).” To his surprise, the conductor agrees and moves him to the adjacent seat near the conductor. These buses have a reserved conductor seat. At this point, he was almost jumping with happiness. Yehhh!!!! The conductor knew the boy’s father and gave the boy a feeling of familiarity. This was the cherry on the cake in terms of feelings of safety. They start chatting about some casual family stuff, as usual. The conductor then goes about the business of checking passengers and helping people settle down.</p>

<p>After having dinner at Bhanjanagar, he returns to the bus and prepares to get some much-needed shuteye for the ghats. The time is about 11 pm. The bus departs the dinner stop and starts its journey via the ghat roads. The lights in the bus are switched off, with a slight blue LED light left on to give a calming journey experience. The curvy roads are dark; a heavy climb is waiting to the Kalinga mountain. The time is just past midnight. The boy is in a deep state of sleep. He felt a mild touch near his private part. He was confused; he is now a bit more conscious. He thought maybe he had seen a dream or that someone had accidentally touched him. He felt the same again, this time a bit strong touch. He is now awake. Yet he keeps acting normally, as if sleeping, but confused. But, still in doubt. The touch becomes more intense. He starts feeling that touch running to his left thigh, then to his inner thigh, slowly moving upward. At this time, he is still unable to process what is happening. What should he do. He is shaking and shivering, not due to cold but “fear” and “disgust”. This keeps happening for a few minutes, and then the boy decides to confront (something opposite to his classical characteristics). He politely tells the conductor to stop touching him this way and that he is uncomfortable. The conductor says, “Hey boy, you just sleep. Relax. Didn’t I give you a front seat?” After a few minutes of the same activities when it does not stop. The boy gets angry and says: “Sir, if you don’t stop this, I am going to shout!” The conductor says, “Shh… silence! People are sleeping. Don’t overreact.” The boy starts crying, albeit silently outside and loudly inside. He is broken. He is shattered. He is “silent”.</p>

<p>As of today, the boy is not really sure for how long this molestation on the bus happened to him. He was always in shock and highly conscious throughout his journey and beyond. He could never sleep on the bus. He was never able to share this with anyone until this day. Today, the boy is 33 years old, and that bus journey in 2010 remains one of the “worst nightmares” of his life. Something was taken from the boy that day, never to be returned, ever, “the dignity”. The boy also regrets not doing anything about it that day for the usual reasons, such as society, family, shame, and fear. Even today, whenever the boy hears news of this kind, a strong, heavy current (called fear) runs down his spine, making his body stiff. At the same time, his brain shows him the imagery of 2010, and its frontal lobe asks, how could the conducted do that act that day? The answer to this the boy has found is simple: “The conductor did that because he could.” There is no other answer that is more rational than this simple one.</p>

<p>I hope parents and family members build strong friendships with their children, creating a bond where children feel safe and comfortable sharing their deepest fears. I wish children find the courage to speak openly without hesitation or fear of judgment, unlike that boy of 2010.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exam over. A scar was waiting.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Travel? Of course!</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/airport/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travel? Of course!" /><published>2024-03-02T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-02T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/airport</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/airport/"><![CDATA[<p>“Yes, you can do it.”, shouts his older cousin, pushing his bicycle from behind and
providing him with some support. At the same time, he rides, for the first time, a 23-inch bicycle
where his tiny legs don’t even reach the pedals. He takes off and, after 24 years, finds himself sitting in a central London airport while staring at his small laptop screen
with a blinking cursor. That little boy is me. Meet me, who loves travelling, preferably
with someone I can open my mind and heart to; otherwise, it is very much “solo”. I love the 
excitement of travelling, especially the preparation that comes before it. No, I don’t like “flying” long hours, which is, for the most part, boring; the crew members dragging some old iron narrow-sized trolley filled with unnecessarily expensive supplements, some children crying and their parents getting exhausted by that, my co-passenger sleeping his heart out with extensive snoring and some using their expensive laptops showing off how to not waste time – These are the people who spend 50 minutes in toilet to pee for 30 seconds but can’t sit in a flight without using their laptop. I just
love the pre-flying routines that start with a bit of panic, arranging stuff to
pack, and the little taxi ride to the train station and then to the airport. I love spending time
at the airport. Today, when I said, “I love airports”, the gentleman (who turns out to be
a professor of theoretical physics at Trinity College Cambridge) was surprised: “You
can’t be serious.” I said, “But I am, sir! I just love airports and those glittering shops in there. The smell of coffee, the not-so-clear announcements. Moreover, I always doubly live
the excitement of travelling.” We had a great chat afterwards on what it means to teach.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, as a kid, I mostly spent time with my grandparents, especially my
grandmother. She was everything to me. She took me everywhere, to every marriage function she
attended, every relative she visited, and every temple she prayed in. I was fortunate
to be with her all the time. Perhaps that is the reason why I really love travelling.
I must say, I always hated those stinking buses. Even as a kid, I always loved to
dress well (well, not by myself, mostly by my mother). She would give me a nice cold bath,
comb my hair, and prepare me with a mini-meal so I wouldn’t cry. But, afterwards, I am given to
my grandma. She would be beside me on the bus, and I would be in the window seat (I used to 
vomit a lot, which was largely due to the burning fuel smell and stinking bus seats. But we
didn’t have much money to choose an alternate option anyway. I guess one small unpleasant travel could help us sail through quite a
lot for the month.)</p>

<p>“Maa, look, those trees are going backwards.” – I shout when the bus moves forward for my
journey and call my grandma to show those trees. I didn’t realise what relative 
motion was at that time. She used to say, “Yes, keep counting them and tell me how many you counted
until we reach.” I almost always fell asleep while counting. It now feels so cute.
I grew up quite fast. I now fly big airlines. I earn well. When I used to sleep under a clear sky, whenever I saw blinking lights moving, I used to shout, “Maa, look one more rocket.”
In last over 2 years alone, I have travelled exactly 
1,42,390 Kilometers (and counting) in the past 1.5 years, which is equivalent to 
3.6 times around the world. Hello, moon! This is almost 40 flights. 
Call Greta Thunberg and show her these statistics. 
(Honestly, I am not too proud of it. But, I make sure I book those flights with lower
carbon emissions. That is the best I could do.)</p>

<p>OK, what does it (“the travelling”) mean to me? It opens my mind a little more. It certainly increases my patience with rather irritating things. I become better as a human. I become
perceptive. I love coming out of my small shell and just swimming around the public. I love 
speaking to people in coffee shops and listening to what they say about various
aspects of life, politics, love, failures, and even travel. Well, not all people talk; some are grumpy, some are egotistical, and some are just idiots. I love pushing their limits, too, sometimes.</p>

<p>Travelling and preparing for a good trip helps me see myself through a different lens. In a big crowd following a queue, you are neither a PhD nor a guy doing AI in Cancer. You are just “You”. Travelling makes me humble. 
I lived most of my early life in a remote village, which 
didn’t even show correctly on Google Maps. 
Travelling gives me that sense of pride that even one with a shallow scope of exploring a life can do so if he dreams of doing so. At this point in my life, I feel fortunate and am very grateful for this excellent
life. I am fulfilling every possible dream one can have as a man and a researcher.
I work at the world’s most prestigious university, and I eat in the world’s most sought-after dining hall of the Trinity College, where once the greats of Jawaharlal Nehru, Alan Turing,
Ramanujan, Hardy, and Amartya Sen had spent much of their time. I work in a field which is
at this point driving the world, “Artificial Intelligence”, to solve human’s greatest fear
“Cancer”.</p>

<p>Above all else, I always (I mean it) miss my grandparents when I travel. They showed me the world, but I couldn’t do the same for them. I always feel a bit closer to them when I sip my coffee at 40000 feet. I wish I could show them what flying means.
Now, my waiting time is running out at the airport, and I just need to call the most
important person in my life. 
Thank you for reading.
See you in my next blog.</p>

<p>TD<br />
Cambridge, UK</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Just the pre-travel]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">0% Engineering, 100% Fun</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/bits0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="0% Engineering, 100% Fun" /><published>2024-02-22T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-22T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/bits0</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2024/bits0/"><![CDATA[<p>“You don’t have to go to class. The institute has a 0% attendance policy. Isn’t that cool!” promotes some random BITS alumni (or not!) on YouTube shorts. You will find many such “strange” and “outrageous” statements if you google BITS Pilani, an institute of eminence in India, which, surprisingly, is not yet an institute of national importance.</p>

<p>I worked at BITS Pilani as an Assistant Professor of Computer Science from 2015 to 2022 (7 years; too long? huh!), and I have never had time to write about my feelings and experiences. There are many beautiful experiences, but I want to pen down a “lecturer” perspective, particularly on one single aspect, in this blog post: <strong>0% attendance</strong>. My views here are my own, and I don’t intend to defame any institute or its students.</p>

<p>Towards the end of my bachelor’s studies (or BTech), I was so much in love with teaching. One day, I became passionate about teaching in one of the country’s premier institutes, such as IITs or BITS Pilani. During BTech, right before the final semester university-level tests, my friends almost always used to crowd my 12x10 room to learn (overnight!) some of the most complex concepts in mathematics, computer science and electronics engineering. I used to be good (fortunately, because I never got a good school education in my village!) in many of these courses. It is not because I used to study every day; it was just that I was so good at analysing and interconnecting concepts and relating them to what I already knew. This teaching during semester exams gave me pure pleasure and motivation to learn more about different topics. I became much better at understanding things by teaching them to my classmates and friends. I must confess, sometimes it does become tiring. At some point, you want to be left alone during exam times. I remember one particular incident; a classmate once told me, “Tirth, tum humko aaj kal padhate nhi ho..” (<em>Tirth, you don’t teach us anymore nowadays.</em>), to which I replied, “No, I don’t; because I don’t have time, and I have a more elevated focus now. I want to teach the best engineering students one day. I am preparing for that.” This may sound too proudy, but, trust me, things were different in those days. Sometimes, it took my full day of energy to understand a concept myself. I didn’t want to become an easy guide to people who hadn’t even tried it themselves so they could just vomit those in their answer sheets the next day. Good education is not free, you know. Remember a dialogue from the movie “Batman”: “If you’re good at something, never do it for free.”, says the Joker (the legendary actor, Late Heath Ledger), although he meant it mainly in the context of money.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, skipping directly to August 2015 at BITS, I was fortunate to be associated with Professor Ashwin, who used to teach artificial intelligence (AI) to 3rd- and 4th-year undergrads. (He later became my doctoral supervisor, a fantastic colleague and, most importantly, the biggest mentor one can wish for in life.) The first day I entered a BITS classroom, Prof. A was teaching the concept of “discrete search” in AI (I think!), I was shocked to see far fewer students than enrolled (<em>by the way, those who used to regularly attend later go on to the best universities or industries in the world and are very successful in their lives, probably one of the most intelligent and humble bunch I have seen in my life at BITS</em>). I asked myself, why would a student not attend a class taken by a world-class professor (who used to teach at Oxford)? I have been taught during my engineering by very passionate teachers, but I had never seen the way Prof. A used to teach. Let me say that he doesn’t (didn’t) teach. He just makes you think at a higher level, using what you already know from before during your early engineering and high-school studies, and gets the answers out of you. This allows you to not remember a thing but rather just see how simple concepts can be used to build complex concepts. Anyway, I adapted some of his teaching and thinking styles later on. In my 7 years at BITS, I almost always taught a course with Prof. A. We used to see very good enrollments (maybe because the courses, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, and AI, were too popular and for the right reasons). I have learned a lot from my students, from their in-classroom questions to their discussion post-lecture and independently. This has contributed significantly to what I am as a person today.</p>

<p>As a lecturer, I spent at least 2 hours before every lecture, which is worth every effort. That feeling when a lecture goes according to plan can be highly gratifying. For me, it almost always felt like a TED talk, except in this case, there is two-way communication and substantial use of blackboard (in BITS, greenboards). I have always loved an interactive lecture session, irrespective of whether I am attending a class or I am taking one. I still miss those days when a student corrected me. It has been quite some time, actually! I miss those days.</p>

<p>Let me now take you through my memory lane of class-attendance characteristics through a semester session. The very first lecture, right after a semester enrollment, is full-house. As a lecturer, you will see (almost) all the faces with determined mindsets: “This semester, I am really going to focus on study.” or “This semester, I am surely going to talk to her and ask her out for a coffee.” And then, as the weeks progress, you will see an exponential drop in attendance, and post mid-term exams, the attendance almost touches the X-axis. This is depressing! I have heard some professors used to have a strict attendance rule (you get 10% of the score if you attend 70% of classes or something like that). I never attempted that, and neither do I like that.</p>

<p>I have also done my bachelor studies in an excellent engineering college, and we used to have a 75% attendance policy. It used to be scary that if you were even at 73%, you could not write mid-term and university exams. Basically, you fail!!! There were courses I loved (such as Mathematics, Programming, Algorithms, Theory of Computation, etc.) for which I was always on time for class. There were courses I didn’t like (such as Software Management and Computer Networks, which required remembering things). Still, I used to maintain the cut-off of 75% attendance so I didn’t have to call my parents and say I failed a university exam. But, over time in my career, I have realised that I am incredibly grateful and thankful for that 75% attendance policy, due to which, even if disinterested, I sat in the class. I listened to those chalk sounds and the teachers’ messages. It really made a big difference in the later part of my career. Those concepts that I was once not interested in but listened to in the class helped me relate concepts on a deeper level. I never wanted to study so-called “Inter-personal Communication”, but I can’t imagine that a boring course would be so helpful in my career, helping me deal with people from different parts of the world. That boring “Software Testing” course has helped me write better programs for Machine Learning. I now wonder what encourages “good” students <strong>NOT</strong> to attend lectures in BITS.</p>

<p>The institute at Goa hosts world-class faculties, most trained in top-tier universities or research labs of the world and are more suited to teach engineering than the ones who taught me engineering during my bachelor days. But, I always wondered why our students won’t attend the classes. Over time, I have been able to narrow down to two probable reasons (I can be wrong, of course): (1) The lecturer doesn’t know how to do a good job at delivering concepts or engaging students, and (2) Peer groups influence students to not attend class. The first is a no-brainer: Not all good researchers are good teachers. They would do tremendous justice to leave teaching and just focus on their small world of research. The second is interesting! During our growing-up phase (usually, in engineering, we are around 18-21 years old), we want to “show off”. We want to show we are studs. We are filled with that inflated sense of pride as if attending lectures would take away that fake pride. We won’t now be called a semi-leader of the pack we have around us.</p>

<p>My focus here is on those students who fall below the mean of the near-normal distribution (if we assume two extremes: Students who do exceptionally well in academics and Students who do extremely well in co-curricular activities). My question to that lower-middle bunch: <strong>What do you think you are doing?</strong> Trust me, I have seen and taught 1000s of students and have closely followed some of their life progression, and I have just one thing to say: <em>Just beep-ing go to the lectures</em>. That’s it. Don’t listen to random videos and Quora posts on why it is so great to have a 0% attendance; do not get influenced by these and spoil your life. Those guys who write and say those things need either immediate medical attention or require help understanding the real reason behind why BITS has this policy in the first place. Honestly, I never read the BITS policy book, and I can’t say whether <em>such a policy exists or is just an assumed norm</em>. It is nothing to be proud of if you don’t know what that entails. So, stop taking things literally and promote nonsense. You don’t realise you are repelling good teachers from your life. You disrespect them, their efforts and time, and their pure interest in doing something good. You don’t realise that those teachers who once felt so motivated don’t want to teach anymore, and you guys are the sole reason for that. Either fall in the extremes of that probability distribution or just attend the lectures. Even if you don’t learn anything, you will become good at sailing through a boring 50-minute meeting, which, believe me, will be a routine thing in your post-BITS life. Talk to those teachers and ask about their failures in life and what they could have done better in different spheres of life. You can learn so much about life in just 10 minutes of interacting with a professor from BITS, and trust me, all of them will be okay to indulge you.</p>

<p>I have always realised one should study not only to get a job with a very high salary package and stock option but to be humble, generous, compassionate, and a better human overall. Try to focus on yourself and your own growth. It is time to grow as an individual. So stop weighing teachers with how much money they earn – None of them are there to make big money, and all of them could have easily made a fortune if they wanted to. The reason is more profound and novel than you can imagine. So, keep calm, (<em>optional: take a shower</em>), pack your bag, and attend the lectures. You will thank yourself later.</p>

<p>I am posting this because I care, and it hurts me, both as a BITS alumnus and an ex-faculty member. If you were one of my students or are a current BITS student and felt hurt by reading this, then you probably fall in that lower-mean bunch. I am very much okay if you are sad and affected. All the students who had nothing else to do but come to my lectures are doing fantastically well in their careers and personal lives. And the same probably goes for many other courses. Most are still in touch with me, even after all of us have left BITS. How we say it: <strong>“Once a BITSian, always a BITSian!”</strong> Let’s hold that BITSian flag high!</p>

<p>–<br />
2:07 PM: “Hi Dash, what do you want?”; “Hey Tom, can I get a small Americano and an apricot croissant, please!”</p>

<p>TD<br />
Cambridge, UK</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Too proud of stupidity?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Muktishikha – by Shraddha</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/sd2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Muktishikha – by Shraddha" /><published>2023-08-02T04:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-02T04:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/sd2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/sd2/"><![CDATA[<p><em>A story written by my sister Shraddha on “friendship”. Some of the Odia texts might look odd; This is mainly due to an underlying encoding issue with markdown.</em></p>

<p>ଜଣେ ପ୍ରକୃତ ବନ୍ଧୁ ହେବା ବଡ଼ ଦାୟିତ୍ୱ ।ଏଥିପାଇଁ ଆପଣଙ୍କୁ ବିଶ୍ୱସ୍ତ ସତ୍ୟପରାୟଣ, ଆନ୍ତରିକ, ମିତ୍ରଭାବାପନ୍ନ, କ୍ଷମାଶୀଳ ,ଦୟାଶୀଳ,  ମୁକ୍ତହୃଦୟ ହେବାକୁ ପଡ଼େ। ସାହାଯ୍ୟ, ସମର୍ଥନ, ଓ ସହାନୁଭୂତି ଦେବାକୁ ପ୍ରସ୍ତୁତ ହୋଇ ରହିବାକୁ ହେବ। 
କ୍ଷମାଶୀଳ ,ଦୟାଶୀଳ, ଆନ୍ତରିକ ଏ ସବୁ ରୁ ମନେପଡ଼ିଲା  କିଛି ଖାଟାମିଠା କାହାଣୀ ଯୁକ୍ତ ୩ ପଢ଼ିବା ସମୟର। ତାରିଖ ୨୮ ସେପ୍ଟେମ୍ବର ୨୦୧୮ ମଧ୍ୟାନ୍ନ ପରେ ,ସମୟ ପ୍ରାୟ ୩.00 P.M ରୁ ୪.୦୦P.M । ଶିଖା college ରୁ ଆସି ଟିକିଏ ବିଶ୍ରାମ ନେଇଥାଏ।  ମନରେ ଅନେକ ପ୍ରଶ୍ନ ଥାଏ।  ମନଟା ଭାରି ଭାରି ଲାଗୁଥାଏ। ସତେ ଯେପରି ; ସେ ସମସ୍ତଙ୍କ ଦୁଃଖର କାରଣ. !</p>

<p>ଶିଖା ଏମିତି ଦୁଃଖ କରିବା ପଛରେ ମଧ୍ୟ କିଛି କାରଣ ରହିଥିଲା ଓ ସେ କାରଣ  ଟି ହେଲା ସେ ରହୁଥିବା ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସକୁ  ରହିବାକୁ ଆସିଥିବା ଜଣଙ୍କ ସହ ଶିଖାର ଝଗଡ଼ା ହୋଇଥିଲା ଓ  ସେ ଝଗଡ଼ା ପାଇଁ ଶିଖାକୁ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସର ମାଲିକଙ୍କ ଠାରୁ ଗାଳି ଶୁଣିବାକୁ ପଡିଥିଲା।
ଏ ସବୁ ଭାବିବା ଭିତରେ ତା’ର କୋଠରୀ କୁ ଜଣେ ନୂଆ ଝିଅ ଟେ ପ୍ରବେଶ କଲା। ତା’ର କୋଠରୀରେ ଥିବା ଅନ୍ୟ ସହପାଠୀ ମନେ ନୂଆ ଝିଅ ସହ କଥା ହେଲେ। ଶିଖା ଚୁପହୋଇ ବସିଥିଲା।  ଶିଖାର ପୂର୍ବ ଝଗଡ଼ା ଓ ଚୁପଚାପ ହୋଇ ବସିବାର କାରଣ ହେଉଛି ;- ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସରେ ଛୋଟିଆ କୋଠରୀ ମଧ୍ୟରେ ଅଧିକ ପିଲାଙ୍କୁ ରଖା ଯାଇଥିଲା। ଯାହା ଫଳରେ ଜିନିଷ ପତ୍ର ଗୁଡ଼ିକ ରଖିବାରେ ସମସ୍ୟା ଦେଖା ଯାଉଥିଲା। କିନ୍ତୁ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସର ମାଲିକ ଏହି ସମସ୍ୟାକୁ ସମାଧାନ କରୁନଥଲା, ଓ ନିଜର ଲାଭ ଲାଭ ପାଇଁ ସେ ସବୁ ସମସ୍ୟା କୁ ଅଣଦେଖା କରୁଥିଲା। ଯାହାଦ୍ୱାରା କି ଅନ୍ୟ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ମାନେ ମଧ୍ୟ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସର ମାଲିକ ଉପରେ ରାଗିଥିଲେ। ଏହା ଥିଲା ଶିଖାର ରାଗିବା କାରଣ।</p>

<p>ଶିଖା ନିଜ ଭାଗ୍ୟକୁ  ମଧ୍ୟ କୋଶୁ ଥିଲା, ଓ ଭଗବାନଙ୍କୁ ମନେମନେ ପ୍ରଶ୍ନ କରୁଥିଲା ଯେ ସବୁବେଳେ ମୋ ସହ କାଇଁ ଏମିତି ହୁଏ ???</p>

<p>ଏ ସବୁ ଭାବିବା ଭିତରେ ତାଙ୍କ ସହିତ ନୂଆ ରହିବାକୁ ଆସିଥିବା ଝିଅ ଟି ଶିଖା କୁ ପ୍ରଶ୍ନ କଲା “ଯୁକ୍ତ ତିନି ପ୍ରଥମ ବର୍ଷର ପାଠପଢ଼ା ଆରମ୍ଭ  ହୋଲାଣି କି ନାଇଁ ?  ନୂଆ ଝିଅ ର ନାଁ ମୁକ୍ତି।  ମୁକ୍ତି ଜାଣିନଥିଲା ଶିଖା ତା ଠାରୁ ବଡ଼ ବୋଲି। ମୁକ୍ତିର କଥା ଶୁଣି ନିଜର ଭାବନା ଭିତରେ ବୁଡ଼ି ରହିଥିବା ଶିଖା ରାଗରେ କହିଲା ; ମୁଁ ଯୁକ୍ତ ତିନି ଦ୍ୱିତୀୟ ବର୍ଷର ଛାତ୍ରୀ। ମୁକ୍ତି ଶିଖାର ଏପରି ବ୍ୟବହାର ଦେଖି ଚୁପ ହୋଇଗଲା ଓ ପରେ ଶିଖା କୁ I’m sorry ଦିଦି….କହି ତା ଜୀନିଷ ପତ୍ର ଗୁଡ଼ିକୁ ରଖିଲା, ଓ dairy ରେ କିଛି ଲେଖିଲା ଏବଂ ତା ପରେ ଟିକିଏ ବିଶ୍ରାମ ନେଲା।
ଶିଖା ରାଗିଲା ସିନା ମୁକ୍ତି ଉପରେ କିନ୍ତୁ ସେ ତା ଖରାପ  ବ୍ୟବହାର ପାଇଁ ବହୁତ ଲଜ୍ଜିତ ଥିଲା। କିନ୍ତୁ ସେ ମୁକ୍ତିକୁ କ୍ଷମା ମଧ୍ୟ ମାଗି ପାରୁନଥିଲା।</p>

<p>ମୁକ୍ତି ର ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସକୁ ଆସିବାର ୩ ରୁ ୪ ଦିନ ପରେ  ତାର ଜନ୍ମଦିନ ଥାଏ ୪ ସେପ୍ଟେମ୍ବର ରେ ।  ୪ ସେପ୍ଟେମ୍ବର ରେ ଶିଖା ର college ରେ ତାଙ୍କର ବିଭାଗରେ ନୂଆ ଆସିଥିବା ଛାତ୍ରଛାତ୍ରୀଙ୍କ ସ୍ଵାଗତ ସମାରୋହ  ମଧ୍ୟ  ଥିଲା। ଶିଖା ତା  ବିଭାଗର ସ୍ଵାଗତ ସମାରୋହ ପାଇଁ ବାହାରୁଥାଏ।  ସେ ସମୟରେ ରେ ମୁକ୍ତି ର ସାଙ୍ଗ ମିତା ଆସି ମୁକ୍ତିକୁ ଜନ୍ମ ଦିନର ଶୁଭେଚ୍ଛା ଜଣାଇଲା। ଶିଖା   ମୁକ୍ତିର ଜନ୍ମ ଦିନ କଥା ଜାଣି ମୁକ୍ତି କୁ ଜନ୍ମ ଦିନର ଶୁଭେଚ୍ଛା ଜଣାଇଲା। ତା ପରେ ମୁକ୍ତି, ଶିଖା କୁ  ଦେଖି  ହସି ଦେଲା ଓ କହିଲା thank u.. ଦିଦି। ମୁକ୍ତି ର ଏପରି ବ୍ୟବହାର ଦେଖି, ଶିଖାକୁ ଲାଗିଲା ମୁକ୍ତି ତାକୁ କ୍ଷମା କରିଦେଇଛି, ଓ ସେ ମୁକ୍ତି ସାଙ୍ଗରେ କିଛି ସମୟ କଥା ହେଲା ଓ ପରେ ସେ college ର ସ୍ୱାଗତ ସମାରୋହ କୁ ଗଲା।</p>

<p>ସେଦିନ ସନ୍ଧ୍ୟାରେ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସର ମଧ୍ୟ ସ୍ୱାଗତ ସମାରୋହ ଥିଲା ,ତେଣୁ ଶିଖା college ରୁ ଆସି ପୁଣି ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସର ସ୍ୱାଗତ ସମାରୋହ କୁ ଗଲା। ସେଠାରେ ନୂଆ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ମାନଙ୍କୁ ସ୍ୱାଗତ କରାଗଲା। ସେଠାରେ ମୁକ୍ତିକୁ ଗୀତ ଗାଇ ନିଜର ପରିଚୟ ପ୍ରଦାନ କରିବାକୁ କୁହାଗଲା। ମୁକ୍ତି ଗୀତ ଗାଇ ନିଜର ପରିଚୟ ପ୍ରଦାନ କଲା।</p>

<p>ଶିଖା ଓ ତା’ର ଅନ୍ୟ ସାଙ୍ଗମାନେ ମୁକ୍ତିକୁ ଜନ୍ମ ଦିନର ଶୁଭେଚ୍ଛା ଓ ଶୁଭକାମନା ଜଣାଇଲେ।</p>

<p>Happy birthday Mukti.. :birthday:Happy Happy birth day to u….:birthday::birthday::birthday:। ପ୍ରାରମ୍ଭିକ ଦିନରେ ଝଗଡ଼ାରୁ ଆରମ୍ଭ ହୋଇଥିବା ସମ୍ପର୍କ କେତେବେଳେ ଯେ ମିତ୍ରତାରେ ବଦଳିଗଲା ତାହା ଜଣା ପଡ଼ିଲାନି। ଶିଖା ଓ ମୁକ୍ତି ର ଅନ୍ୟ ଦୁଇଜଣ ସହପାଠୀ ତାଙ୍କର PG ପାଠପଢ଼ା ସାରି ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସରୁ ବିଦୟ ନେଲେ। ଏତିକି ଦିନ ମଧ୍ୟରେ ଶିଖା ଓ ମୁକ୍ତି ଭଲ ସାଙ୍ଗ ହୋଇ ଯାଇଥିଲେ  । ଶିଖା ମୁକ୍ତି ଠାରୁ ବଡ଼। ଶିଖା ମୁକ୍ତିକୁ ନିଜର ସାନ ଭଉଣୀ ପରି ଦେଖୁଥିଲା, ଓ ମୁକ୍ତି ମଧ୍ୟ ଶିଖାକୁ ସମ୍ମାନ  ଦିଏ। ଉଭୟେ ସବୁ କାମ ଏକାଠି କରନ୍ତି, ଓ ସେମାନେ ସବୁ ଜିନିଷ ପତ୍ର ମଧ୍ୟ ଏକା ସାଙ୍ଗରେ ରଖନ୍ତି। ଶିଖାର ମନ କଥାକୁ ମୁକ୍ତି ଭଲଭାବରେ ଜାଣିପାରେ,ଓ ମୁକ୍ତିର ମନ କଥାକୁ ଶିଖା ମଧ୍ୟ ଭଲ ଭାବେ ଜାଣିପାରେ। ପ୍ରତ୍ୟେକ ସମୟରେ ଉଭୟେ ଉଭୟଙ୍କ ସାହାଯ୍ୟ କରନ୍ତି ।ସେମାନେ ବାହାରକୁ ବୁଲିବାକୁ ଗଲେ ମଧ୍ୟ ଏକା ସାଙ୍ଗରେ ଯାଆନ୍ତି। ଏପରିକି ସେମାନେ F.B ମଧ୍ୟ ଗୋଟିଏ ଦିନରେ ସମାନ ସମୟରେ ଖୋଲିଥିଲେ।</p>

<p>ଶିଖା ତା ଜୀବନରେ ଆଗରୁ କେବେ ଜଣେ ଭଲ ବନ୍ଧୁ ପାଇନଥିବା। ଶିଖାର ପ୍ରାୟ ବନ୍ଧୁ ମାନେ ଶିଖାକୁ ନିଜର ଦରକାର ପାଇଁ ବ୍ୟବହାର କରୁଥିଲେ।  ପୂର୍ବରୁ ଏପରି ପରିସ୍ଥିତି ଥିଲା ଶିଖା ଜୀବନରେ। କିନ୍ତୁ ମୁକ୍ତି ଆସିବା ପରେ, ଶିଖା ଜୀବନରେ ଖୁସି ଭରିଯାଇଥିଲା।
କୁହାଯାଏନା କିଛିଟା ସମ୍ପର୍କ ରକ୍ତ ସମ୍ପର୍କର ନହେଲେ ବି ପ୍ରେମ, ସ୍ନେହରେ,ଓ ଆନ୍ତରିକତାର ଡୋରରେ ହୃଦୟକୁ କିଣି ନିଅନ୍ତି। ଏପରି ଥିଲା ଶିଖା ଓ ମୁକ୍ତିର ସମ୍ପର୍କ।</p>

<p>“ Not Sisters by blood…Sisters by heart”…ମୁକ୍ତି ଶିଖାକୁ ସବୁବେଳେ କହେ ଦିଦି ତୁମେ ଏଇ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସରୁ ଚାଲିଗଲା ପରେ ମୁଁ ଏଠି ଏକା ହେଇଯିବି। ଏକଥା ଶୁଣି ଶିଖାକୁ ଟିକେ ଦୁଃଖ ଲାଗେ,କିନ୍ତୁ ସେ ମୁକ୍ତି ଆଗରେ ତା ଭାବନାକୁ
ବ୍ୟକ୍ତ କରିପାରେନି। ଏପରି ଚାଲିଥାଏ ଉଭୟଙ୍କ ଜୀବନର ଗତିପଥ। ଶିଖାର ଯୁକ୍ତ ୩ ଶେଷ ପରୀକ୍ଷା ଥାଏ। କୋରୋନା ଭୂତାଣୁର ପ୍ରଭାବ ଯୋଗୁଁ ଶିଖାର ଯୁକ୍ତ ୩ ଶେଷ ପରୀକ୍ଷା ବାତିଲ ହେଲା ଓ ମୁକ୍ତି ଆଉ ଶିଖା ଉଭୟେ ନିଜର ଘରକୁ ଚାଲିଗଲେ। ଉଭୟଙ୍କ ଆଉ ଦେଖା ହେବକି ନାଇଁ ତାହା ଭାବି ଉଭୟେ ମନ ଦୁଃଖ କରିଥିଲେ। ଛୁଟିରେ ଶିଖାର ଯୁକ୍ତ ୩ ପରୀକ୍ଷା ଫଳ ପ୍ରକାଶ ପାଇଲା ଓ ସେ ଭଲ ନମ୍ବର ରଖି ଉତ୍ତୀର୍ଣ୍ଣ ମଧ୍ୟ ହେଲା। କିନ୍ତୁ ତାପରେ ସେ ପିଜି ଏକକ ପରୀକ୍ଷା ଦେଇଥିଲା କିନ୍ତୁ ସେ ଉତ୍ତୀର୍ଣ୍ଣ ହୋଇ ପାରିଲାନି। ତେଣୁ ସେ ସବୁବେଳେ ମାନସିକ ଚିନ୍ତା ଓ ଦୁଃଖରେ ରହୁଥିଲା । ମୁକ୍ତି ତାକୁ ସବୁବେଳେ ସାହାସ ଦେଉଥିଲା ଓ ନିରାଶ ନହୋଇ ପୁଣି ପରିଶ୍ରମ କରିବାକୁ କହେ। ଏବଂ ଆଶା ରଖ ଦିଦି ସବୁ ସଠିକ୍ ସମୟ ଆସିଲେ ଠିକ ହେବକହି ଆଶ୍ୱାସନା ଦିଏ ।</p>

<p>ଏମିତି କିଛି ସମୟ ବିତିଯାଇଥିଲା ଓ କୋରୋନା ଭୂତାଣୁର ପ୍ରଭାବ ଟିକିଏ କମିବାରୁ ପୁଣି ବିଦ୍ୟାଳୟ ଓ ଅନ୍ୟାନ୍ୟ ଶିକ୍ଷାନୁଷ୍ଠାନ ଖୋଲିଥିଲା । ମୁକ୍ତିର ଯୁକ୍ତ ୩ ଶେଷ ପରୀକ୍ଷା ଥିଲା ତେଣୁ ସେ ତା ଘରୁ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସକୁ ଆସିଲା। ଶିଖା ଓ ମୁକ୍ତି ପୁଣି ଥରେ ଦେଖାହେଲେ ପ୍ରାୟ ଗୋଟେ ବର୍ଷ ପରେ ତାପରେ ଟିକିଏ ବୁଲାବୁଲି କରି  ଶିଖା ତା  ଘରକୁ ଫେରିଲା, ଓ ମୁକ୍ତି ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସକୁ।  ପୁଣିଥରେ କୋରୋନା ଭୂତାଣୁର ପ୍ରଭାବ ବଢ଼ିବା ଯୋଗୁଁ ଶିକ୍ଷାନୁଷ୍ଠାନ ସବୁ ବଂଦ ହୋଇଗଲା ଓ ମୁକ୍ତି ତା ଘରକୁ ଫେରିଗଲା।</p>

<p>କିଛି ଦିନ ପରେ ଶିଖାର ମାଆଙ୍କ ବଦଳି ହୋଇଥାଏ, ଶିଖା ଯୁକ୍ତ ୩ ପଢ଼ୁଥିବା ସ୍ଥାନକୁ। ପୁଣିଥରେ କୋରୋନା ଭୂତାଣୁର ପ୍ରଭାବ କମିବାରୁ ଶିକ୍ଷାନୁଷ୍ଠାନ ଖୋଲିଲା, ଓ ମୁକ୍ତି ତା ଯୁକ୍ତ ୩ ଶେଷ ବର୍ଷର ପରୀକ୍ଷା ଦେବାପାଇଁ ଛାତ୍ରୀ ନିବାସକୁ ଆସିଲା।</p>

<p>ଭେଟ ନପଡ଼ିବାର ଦୁଃଖରେ ଥିବା ମୁକ୍ତି ତା ପ୍ରିୟ ବନ୍ଧୁ ଶିଖା ସହ  ପୁଣି ଥରେ ଦେଖାକଲା। ସେ ଦିନ ପୁଣି ୪ ସେପ୍ଟେମ୍ବର ୨୦୨୧ ମୁକ୍ତିର ଜନ୍ମ ଦିନ ଥିଲା। ଶିଖା ମୁକ୍ତିକୁ ଜନ୍ମ ଦିନର ଶୁଭେଚ୍ଛା ଜଣାଇଲା ଓ କିଛି ଉପହାର ଦେଲା। ପୂର୍ବଦିନ ଗୁଡିକର ସ୍ମୃତି ଉଭୟଙ୍କ ଆଖି ଆଗରେ ନାଚି ଉଠୁଥିଲା। ମୁକ୍ତି ଓ ଶିଖା ଉଭୟେ ଭାବ ବିହୁଳ ହୋଇ ଉଭୟଙ୍କ ଭାବନାକୁ ବ୍ୟକ୍ତ କଲେ। ଉଭୟଙ୍କ ଆଖିରେ ଥିଲା ବିଦାୟର ଦୁଃଖ। ଛଳ ଛଳ ଆଖିରେ ଉଭୟେ ଉଭୟଙ୍କୁ ଚାହିଁ ଏକା ସାଙ୍ଗରେ କହିଲେ ଏଇଟା ବୋଧେ ଆମର ଶେଷ ଦେଖା।  ମୁକ୍ତି କହିଲା ଦିଦି ତୁମପରି ବଂଧୁ ଟେ ପୁଣି  ଜୀବନରେ ମିଳିବ ନା ନାଇଁ ମୁଁ ଜାଣିନି। କିନ୍ତୁ ଭଗବାନଙ୍କ ଠାରେ ମୋର ଏତିକି ପ୍ରାର୍ଥନା ଆମର ବନ୍ଧୁତ୍ୱ ଏପରି  ସାରା ଜୀବନ ରହିଥାଉ। ମୁକ୍ତିର କଥା ଶୁଣି ଶିଖା ତା ଭାବନା ଯେ କେମିତି ଯେ ପ୍ରକାଶ କରିବ ସେଥିପାଇଁ ଶବ୍ଦ ମଧ୍ୟ ପାଉନଥିଲା।  ଉଭୟେ ଉଭୟଙ୍କୁ ଭବିଷ୍ୟତ ଜୀବନ ପାଇଁ ଶୁଭେଚ୍ଛା ଜଣାଇଲେ ଓ ଶେଷରେ ବିଦାୟ ନେଲେ…………………</p>

<p>ଝଗଡ଼ା ରୁ ଆରମ୍ଭ ହୋଇ ବନ୍ଧୁତ୍ୱରେ ଶେଷ ତାଙ୍କର ସେଇ ସମ୍ପର୍କ। ଆଗକୁ ମଧ୍ୟ ଏମିତି ବଜାୟ ରହିବ ଏହି ବନ୍ଧୁତ୍ୱ। ଏଇ   ସୁନ୍ଦର ବନ୍ଧୁତ୍ୱର ମୂଳଦୁଆ ହେଲା କ୍ଷମା।  ପ୍ରାରମ୍ଭ ଦିନର ଝଗଡ଼ା ପାଇଁ ଯଦି ମୁକ୍ତି ଶିଖାକୁ କ୍ଷମା କରି ନଥାନ୍ତା ତେବେ ଏତେ ସୁନ୍ଦର ବନ୍ଧୁତ୍ୱର କାହାଣୀ ମଧ୍ୟ ଲେଖା ହୋଇ ନଥାନ୍ତା।</p>

<p>ଜୀବନରେ ବନ୍ଧୁତ୍ୱକୁ ଟଙ୍କା ପଇସାରେ ତୁଳନା କରି ହୁଏନି। ବରଂ ସ୍ନେହ, ଶ୍ରଦ୍ଧା, ଓ ଭଲ ପାଇବା ଦେଇ ଗଛ ପରି ବଡ଼ କରିବାକୁ ପଡ଼େ। ଜଣେ ପ୍ରକୃତ ବନ୍ଧୁ ତା ବନ୍ଧୁର ଭଲ ସମୟରେ ଥାଉ ଅବା ନଥାଉ କିନ୍ତୁ କଠିନ ସମୟରେ ସାହାଯ୍ୟ କରିବାକୁ ପଛଘୁଞ୍ଚା ନଦେଇ ପତିତ ଅବସ୍ଥାରୁ ଉଠି ଠିଆ ହେବାକୁ ପ୍ରେରଣା ଦିଏ ତା ବନ୍ଧୁକୁ। ଏହାର ଜ୍ୱଳନ୍ତ ଉଦାହରଣ;- ମୁକ୍ତି ଓ ଶିଖା…….(# ମୁକ୍ତିଶିଖା) A true story about Friendship…..(#MUKTISHIKHA)…</p>]]></content><author><name>Shraddhanjali Dash</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A beautiful story on friendship.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shraddha’s Write-ups</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/sd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shraddha’s Write-ups" /><published>2023-07-25T04:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-25T04:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/sd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/sd/"><![CDATA[<p><em>These are some short poems and feelings scribbled by my sister, Shraddhanjali Dash. These poems are in Odia. Both of us are working together to translate these to English.</em></p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/sd/1.jpeg" data-zoomable="" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/sd/2.jpeg" data-zoomable="" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/sd/3.jpeg" data-zoomable="" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/sd/4.jpeg" data-zoomable="" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/sd/5.jpeg" data-zoomable="" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<p><em>If you like these, please share your thoughts <a href="mailto:dashtirtharaj@gmail.com">with me</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Short poems from her pen.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy (Grand)Mother’s Day!</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/mothers-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy (Grand)Mother’s Day!" /><published>2023-05-11T04:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-11T04:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/mothers-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2023/mothers-day/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a letter to my grandmother, who I always believed and accepted as my “mother” and called her “mama”, who cared for me, protected me, and was always there for me when I needed her.</em></p>

<p>Dearest and sweetest Mama,</p>

<p>First, I miss you, and I am sure you miss me too, wherever you are. I am doing good; I am healthy; I am fit. I play, work, swim, and do gym (<em>not in this particular order, of course</em>); my life is fantastic.</p>

<p>Yes, I do look up in the sky to find you once and try to get a glimpse of your most beautiful face with that smile, in search of that love and warmth that you provided to make me what I am today, that selfless love and care that I always needed to be a good human being, and of course, those little scoldings that I must have needed when I was being nasty.</p>

<p>I remember especially the day I was playing cricket with the wall in our rented mini-house, which we called “Home”, and I broke that brown-round wall clock and the way you shouted at me. I wouldn’t say I liked it; I was sad and angry. But, you know that was needed, for sure, to teach me to realise the importance of resources. Do you remember how we both sat together and tried to fix the broken clock back to the way it was, but we weren’t successful? That day you taught me things that you can break easily doesn’t mean you can fix them or may never be able to.</p>

<p>I do miss those days when you used to cook for the three of us (you, budhabapa, “my grandfather”, and myself). I used to be there around you talking about how things went at my college (10+2 Science) and how I answered some questions, or how one of my teachers praised me in the class, or how math comes easily to me. I miss those days, mama, when you used to serve me and budhabapa and forced me to eat just one more roti. But, when he used to eat more, you used to make fun of him. I wish you both were there in my life now and forever or at least I could live one more day with you to eat your hand-made rotis. I am not getting them here in San Diego. I don’t get those tasty alu-kobi tarakari (Potato-Cabbage Curry) that I used to love.</p>

<p>And, remember, all those days when I went to college and coaching, and you never missed a day to come to the door and say “bye, take care”? You taught me to always be honest, gentle, trustworthy, and always tell the truth, no matter what. I am sure I have lived up to your expectations. Maybe, sometimes, I have been too truthful, and you know what, I feel damm proud of it like you always wanted me to be.</p>

<p>Ok, let me not make you too emotional now, and share the happy stuff. I am in America. I get to fly 30 hours straight, you know. They give a lot of food, all the time, every 2-3 hours. Isn’t that fun! Neh! Not so much. It’s boring. Whenever I fly I remember the day I flew first time in my life, Air India, Bangalore to Raipur via Mumbai in 2013. How Budhabapa was so proud of me? You guys gave me a life, you know. Sorry again, I am going emotional here; what can I do? You never taught me how to control my emotions. I live in a coastal place. My landlords are lovely; they are like family. I earn in dollars, mama, and guess, what is the exchange rate? 1 dollar is equivalent to 80 rupees. I could buy an excellent piece of Sambalpuri saree for you for just less 200-300 dollars. I could take you to the world’s best shop to get that piece. I hold an iPhone 13 (guess the cost? 80000 Indian rupees; sorry, don’t scold me now!), but who do I speak with, mama. You don’t have a phone to connect.</p>

<p>How do I speak with you? For once, for a few sec, if I could just say how much “I love you”.</p>

<p>I am SO SORRY, mama, I wasn’t there for you during your last days; I sincerely wish I could have cared less about my job and PhD studies and taken a few days of leave to sit with you, maybe give you a head massage and massage your strong legs. I wish I could just share with you how much you meant to me and how you and budhabapa gave me a life. You both are not there now, at least physically, but you are there with me. See, see, what the “dedication” in my PhD thesis reads:</p>

<div align="center">
THIS THESIS IS DEDICATED TO MY GRANDPARENTS:<br />
Shri Satyanarayan Dash (Grandfather) <br />
Smt Sirisha Dash (Grandmother) <br />
They were, therefore I am.
</div>

<p>And I mean it.</p>

<p>I am living a life that one coming from the kind of background I come from could only imagine, and I always give all the credit to you and budhabapa. Wish I could be like you guys one day. I will be; not old like you guys, though ;-)</p>

<p>You know people wish for “Mother’s Day” nowadays. We didn’t know such a thing existed in the first place. Did we? Don’t you think it is only correct to wonder, “Which day is not a Mother’s Day?”. For me, every day will be a Mother’s Day. You are my Yashoda, and it will always be “Happy Grandmother’s Day”.</p>

<p>There are a lot of updates, mama; it is getting late. I need to sleep soon. Otherwise, you will scold me again. Just take care, and I am sure you are taking care of budhabapa; don’t argue with each other over there; I won’t like it. You guys are not kids anymore. Haha! See, I have grown up now but not wiser enough.</p>

<p>Too many updates to give you. I know I won’t get a response from your end. You don’t have internet and a PC. Even if you had one, you wouldn’t know how to type and send an email. Would you? I am not making fun; just accept it :-) I know you will get excited about learning how these tech stuff work. And, I almost forgot to tell you, I do “AI” for a living, and you know what “It doesn’t make rotis.”</p>

<p>Ok, bye now. Be there.</p>

<p>I love you, and my tears will always wait for your saree …</p>

<p>Yours,<br />
Bubun</p>

<p><em>To all the mothers and grandmothers who have made their children’s dreams come true, a grand salute and pranamami namaste. You make this world worth living. Happy Mother’s Day.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You meant the world to me.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sneaked in through those days</title><link href="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2022/happy-halloween/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sneaked in through those days" /><published>2022-10-31T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2022/happy-halloween</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tirtharajdash.github.io/blog/2022/happy-halloween/"><![CDATA[<p>I had absolutely no feeling at times, and there were times when my mind would rush me through a dense traffic of countless thoughts with innumerable checks in my decision tree. What if, this, else, that, then what if this. It never ended at times, making me go crazy without being able to share what I felt or was feeling with anyone other than my depressed self.
I would eat something and go to bed to get some shuteye, only to realise that it was already 4 am and I had never rested. My brain never rested. There were also days when I would never sleep for over 72 hours (Yes, I counted the hours).</p>

<p>Over time, I realised I had been losing pleasure and joy in life and would have no interest in what and how my close ones were doing; I started losing concentration and focus in daily activities. I used to think there would be no time when I would be happy ever again. Being a food lover, I used to love varieties of foods. But, I started losing my appetite, often eating just one meal to eating just a biscuit packet in a day to deal with that knot in my stomach. I had no idea how to describe these feelings, these worse nightmares of my daily life, to anyone. Some days would go by with severe headaches and body aches, maybe because I was too weak and inactive with low energy in my body. There have also been days when I would contemplate extreme steps in life. But, then a part of me somewhere would shout at me and say, “Are you serious? Are you this weak? Have you not seen and been through hard phases earlier? Now, what happened? You are breaking!” I would attempt to stop that “sane” person inside my head and say, “Shut up! What do you know!” Then, it goes silent. “Yah, Yah! But remember, I am not leaving you alone.” These feelings became more vigorous and haunting when news about a few unfortunate incidents occurred in India. Some of these were that of Two Hindu saints who were being lynched and killed by the locals in Palghar, Maharashtra; a pregnant elephant being forced to eat bombs and due to which she died a horrible death in Kerala; and Sushant Singh Rajput, a great Bollywood actor who I admired, passed away under questionable circumstances. I went numb after learning about these incidents, going into that phase of extreme sadness and a pit from which I thought I would never get out. Some of these feelings would come out in intense anger, forcing me to break physical stuff, one of which was my badminton racquet – that once was one of my favourite companions and breaking that coffee mug that an old friend of mine had gifted me with so much love. I neither felt proud of these actions nor thought these were sane, and that feeling would make me sad and low. I never wanted to leave my house, sometimes closed for days and weeks, perhaps, and whenever I came out, people wouldn’t notice what I was going through. The idea of keeping a “fake” smile on the face would probably have helped; I don’t know. But, somewhere, I always needed help. I wanted to talk. I wanted to shout about what I am going through. I would call some of my friends, only to realise that they are already dealing with so much that I would not burden them with pity. Also, I didn’t know what I would say to them. Do I say, “Hey, I am feeling like this?” How the hell would I express what I am feeling? Even when I tried that, I often got responses like “Everything will be okay; this is just a bad phase. This too shall pass.” No, I didn’t want your philosophical extremities now; I just wanted you to “listen” to me.</p>

<p>This process had been going on for months, shortly after COVID hit and just after, some of my most beautiful personal decisions were turning out to be not very favourable for my life, or at least these feelings made me think so. However, I trust that I may have positively impacted the lives of people involved in these stages. I seemed to have sensed everybody was in some phase like mine or maybe Not. I succumbed to this for nearly two years until something unexpected yet beautiful happened in my life (Well, that for later). But, if someone sees the things that are seen about a person from the outside, perhaps the personal achievements and progress that I made over the years, these stages of life would never surface anywhere. However, I am damn proud of those achievements and progress.</p>

<p>Around somewhere, there was still a signal or an indescribable instance in my head that touched me once and said, “I know you are feeling like this. But, can you do this?” It further said, just remember that “Hope is a good thing and hold on to that.” I said, “what a big deal. Yes, I can.” I started uttering this one sentence “Hope is a good thing.”, whenever I felt sad and that undiagnosed feeling.</p>

<p>We are nearing the end of 2022, a year I thought I would never witness. I now feel newer and better and happier than ever. I feel so good nowadays and get a sweet smile when I look back.</p>

<p>For those who read this blog and reached this sentence, if you ever felt or feel like you have been through these “phases” of life, remember, I am there for you.</p>

<p>Wishing you a lot of fun and yummy treats. Happy Halloween!</p>

<p>From:
<br />
T
<br />
San Diego, CA</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[you never knew that part of me]]></summary></entry></feed>